Guide to the Charles and Annette O'Flaherty Papers WAG.142
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Charles and Annette O'Flaherty Papers
1937-1999
1952-1970
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
O'Flaherty, Charles
O'Flaherty, Annette
O'Flaherty, Brendan
WAG.142
1 Linear Feet in 1 record carton.
Annette O'Flaherty was a trade-union activist and president of the CIO Women's League of New Jersey from the mid-1950s through the early 1960s. Her papers in this collection include constitutions, convention records, newsletters, and correspondence with leading labor and political figures in New Jersey, as well as general material documenting the history of women's role in the labor movement. Charles O'Flaherty was the eldest of three brothers who fought in Spain during the Spanish Civil War as volunteers in the Abraham Lincoln Brigade. Following his youngest brother Edward's death in 1978, Charles acquired some of Edward's writings on his experience in Spain. These writings, and Charles's International Brigades identity card, are included in this collection. Twenty-four photographs are also included which document Annette O'Flaherty's work with the CIO Women's League of New Jersey, Abraham Lincoln Brigade veterans and the O'Flaherty family.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Annette O'Flaherty in 1997. Additional items were donated by Annette and Charles' son Brendan O'Flaherty in 2000. The accession numbers associated with these gifts are 1997.004 and 1997.016.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Historical/Biographical Note
Annette Doyle O'Flaherty was born in New York City. She graduated from Columbia High School in 1936 and from Mount Holyoke College with a B.A. with honors in Economics in 1940. In July of 1940, she went to work on the editorial staff of Springfield Newspapers until the papers stopped publication because of a strike in September 1946. While working for Springfield Newspapers, Annette served as executive secretary of the Springfield Newspaper Guild, Local 28 until October 1947. At that time she became the National Coordinator for the United Nations Appeal for Children and American Overseas Aid until the organization dissolved in June 1948. Annette returned to Springfield where she became secretary and campaign manager for a joint AFL-CIO political committee organized for the 1948 political election year. The committee was successful in defeating three anti-labor referenda and helped to elect a Congressman.
Annette also served as secretary of the Western Massachusetts CIO Council for four years and was assistant director of the Union Counseling Program. She became the state president of the CIO Women's League of New Jersey in the 1950s after settling in Newark, New Jersey with her husband Charles.
Charles (Charlie) O'Flaherty was born in South Boston and graduated from Norwood, MA High School in 1924. He was the oldest of three brothers, all of whom eventually volunteered for service in the Spanish Civil War (using the original version of their family name, Flaherty). He attended Colby College on scholarship but quit after two years to help support his family. He became interested in the labor movement and socialism while in college and was influenced by the hunger marchers he saw on Boston Common. His first job was working as a purchasing manager for Barnes and Noble. In the early 1930's, Charles worked for the Cambridge Rubber Company in Cambridge Massachusetts.
In 1936, Charles went to Spain and was a leader of the Irish Section of the International Brigades. He was wounded on the Jarama Front, where he served with the Abraham Lincoln Brigade infantry. Charles was sent home in 1937 as a result of severe injuries to his arm. He went on a nation-wide tour with his brother Frank, who was also wounded in Spain, to raise funds for the Friends of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade.
The youngest Flaherty brother, Edward, was an infantry commander at Jarama. He was an auto mechanic who served in World War II with an Army transportation unit in Germany. Following his return from the war, he settled in Paterson, New Jersey. Edward (Eddie) died on July 13, 1978.
In 1940 Charles accepted a job organizing for the United Electric Workers (UE). He was an early member of the Marine Workers Industrial Union and was a delegate to the National Maritime Union (NMU) convention in 1945. Charles left for sea again at the beginning of World War II and spent the war on the Murmansk Run as a member of the NMU.
Charles O'Flaherty married Annette Doyle in November 1948 and settled in Newark, N.J.; they had two sons, Sean and Brendan. Charles worked for the Worthington Pump Co. and served as president of Local 55 of the International Brotherhood of Firemen, Oilers, and Maintenance Mechanics, AFL-CIO. The O'Flahertys remained active in the anti-war, anti-nuclear, feminist and other progressive political movements. Charles O'Flaherty died on June 28, 1984, and Annette in 2000.
Scope and Content Note
This collection includes materials pertaining to both the Flaherty brothers' involvement in the Spanish Civil War and Annette O'Flaherty's presidency of the CIO Women's League of New Jersey. Included in the Spanish Civil War materials are Edward O'Flaherty's writings and correspondence, Charles O'Flaherty's notes and letters, and Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade mailings. Highlights include Edward Flaherty's identification card from Spain and his writing about his experience in the Spanish Civil War. Materials pertaining the CIO Women's League of New Jersey include correspondence, constitutions, convention records, newsletters, and publications from the national CIO. Highlights include correspondence with leading labor and political figures in New Jersey. The collection also includes twenty-four photographs documenting the O'Flaherty family, Spanish Civil War veterans and CIO Women's League events.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into three series:
Series I: Spanish Civil War Materials, 1937-1984
Series II: Trade-Union Activities, 1940-1968
Series III: Photographs, 1959-1999
All series are arranged alphabetically.
Folders are arranged alphabetically by topic within each series.
The files are grouped into two series:
Missing Title
I, Spanish Civil War Materials
II, Trade-Union Activities
Separated Material
One rolled photograph was separated and placed with other rolled photographs for preservation.
Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Participation, American; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939.; Photographs.; Soldiers |z United States |v Biography.; Women labor leaders.; Newsletters.; Correspondence.; Newark (N.J.).; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Campaigns.; Reports.; Personal papers.; Congress of Industrial Organizations (U.S.); O'Flaherty, Charles; Flaherty, Edward; O'Flaherty, Annette; Spain. Ejército Popular de la República. Abraham Lincoln Battalion; CIO Women's League of New Jersey; Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade; Krebs, Paul J. (Paul Joseph), 1912-1996; Meyner, Robert B.; Meany, George, 1894-1980; Reuther, Walter, 1907-1970; O'Flaherty, Edward; Minish, Joseph G.; New Jersey State Industrial Union Council; AFL-CIO. Committee on Political Education; O'Flaherty, Annette; O'Flaherty, Brendan
- Series I: Spanish Civil War Materials, 1937-1984
  - Flaherty, Edward (?): Authorization for Hospital Visit, [1937] (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Flaherty, Edward: Identification Card, [1937] (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - O'Flaherty, Charles, undated, 1982-1984 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - O'Flaherty, Edward: Correspondence, undated, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - O'Flaherty, Edward: Writings, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade, 1977-1980 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Series II: Trade-Union Activities, 1940-1968
  - CIO Women's League of New Jersey-Committee on Political Education (COPE) AFL-CIO, 1958-1959 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - CIO Women's League of New Jersey-CIO PAC Conference on Family Participation in PAC, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - CIO Women's League of New Jersey: Constitution, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - CIO Women's League of New Jersey: Correspondence, 1955-1959 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - CIO Women's League of New Jersey: Correspondence with IUE, UAW, CWA, National CIO, and National CIO Auxiliaries, 1954-1955 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - CIO Women's League of New Jersey: Essex-West Hudson Chapter, 1956-1961 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - CIO Women's League of New Jersey: First Convention, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - CIO Women's League of New Jersey: Fourth Annual Convention Conference, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - CIO Women's League of New Jersey: The League Reporter, 1952-1955 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - CIO Women's League of New Jersey: Member List, 1953-1954 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - CIO Women's League of New Jersey: National CIO Women's Conference, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - CIO Women's League of New Jersey: News Bulletin/Newsletter, 1955-1957 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - CIO Women's League of New Jersey: Newspaper Clippings, 1955-1959 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - CIO Women's League of New Jersey: Officers' Report, 1957-1961 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - CIO Women's League of New Jersey: Organizational Material, 1949-1962 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - CIO Women's League of New Jersey: Resolutions, undated, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - CIO Women's League of New Jersey: Second Annual Convention, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - CIO Women's League of New Jersey: Steering Committee, undated, 1954-1955 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - CIO Women's League of New Jersey: Supervised Shower Programs, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - CIO Women's League of New Jersey: The Union Maid, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - CIO Women's League of New Jersey: Vaccines, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Government Regulation and Control and Concentration of American Business, Annette Doyle Honors Paper, May 27, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - IUE-AFL-CIO, Local 447 Elections, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - National CIO Community Service Center, undated, 1953-1954 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - New Jersey State Industrial Union Council AFL-CIO: Report on New Jersey, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - New Jersey State CIO Council, 1955-1961 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Newark Pre-School Council Annual Staff Report, 1967-1968 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Springfield Newspaper Guild, Local 28, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Western Massachusetts CIO Council, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 35)
- Series III: Photographs, 1959-1999
  - Abraham Lincoln Brigade Veterans (Charles O'Flaherty, Ed Flaherty and Paul Burns), 1970s (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Community Services Dinner, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Miscellaneous, circa 1959 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - O'Flaherty Family, 1999, undated (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Testimonial dinner for Mrs. Carl Holderman, CIO Women of New Jersey, 1959-10-21 (Box Shared Tamiment 032)